Smitaj Suresh Pawar
                                        
        Contact No.
 years of overall IT experience.
Working as AI Engineer and Azure Solution Architect.
 Years of experience in Microsoft azure BI and data Solution development and Data Analytics.
Expert knowledge Microsoft Azure Fabric onelake
warehouse, Azure AI Foundry, Azure ML Studio, Data Factory 
, Mapping Data Flow, Azure Blob Storage, Azure Data Bricks, Azure Data Lake, Azure Synapse Analytics, Azure SQL Server, Azure DWH, Logic App, Azure function, Data purview, azure HDInsight, key vault, Azure Devops CI-CD, Azure SQL Server, Azure synapse DWH, Azure Analysis Service, T-SQL, Dimensional Modelling, MSBI Tools - SSIS
Parallel Data Warehousing
, Hive, Terraform etc.
Experience in Microsoft Fabric Lakehouse, Datawarehouse, data pipelines, Semantic modelling.
Experience to build AI solution using various technologies like Azure AI Foundry, Google Gemini AI studio
Antigravity, large language model 
, Agentic AI, Lang chain, GitHub Copilot Studio, Cursor etc.
Experience in Microsoft Power BI reporting tool.
Experience in Google cloud including Google Big Query, Google storage, Pub-Sub, Google function for 1 year.
Worked in Alteryx data blending tool for around 6 months.
Experience in Agile
 Requirement Gathering 
 Analysis, Design, Coding, Code reviews, Configuration control, Efforts Estimations, Providing Technical Solutions and Performance Tuning.   
Worked on various Project and POC
s on different technologies like large language model 
, RAG, finetuning, evaluation, Reinforcement learning 
, AI Agent, Transfer learning, ELK 
Elasticsearch and Kibana
, Denodo, Talend and designed POC in Machine learning, Deep Learning, Data Mining, NLP,FastAPI,Open CV using python and R language.
Worked 1 year at onsite UK location as Azure data developer for Coca Cola client.
Customer Engagement experience while handling various projects with a good track record of ensuring repeat and increase in business.
Microsoft certified Azure Solutions Architect Expert.
Certified Deep Learning Engineer with Tensorflow and Keras.
Professional Experience
Currently working as AI Engineer
Azure Solution Architect
Data engineer in Nouryon, Navi Mumbai from Sep 2023 to till date.
Worked as an Azure data engineer
Google data engineer in Atos from May 2021 to Sep 2023. 
Worked as an Azure data engineer in LTI from Mar 2021 to May 2022. 
Worked as an Azure data engineer in CitiusTech from Jan 2020 to Mar 2021. 
Worked as an Azure data engineer
BI Developer in Mastek from June 2014 to Jan 2020. 
Professional Achievement
Performer of the Year Award for 2025 in Nouryon. 
Microsoft Certified
 Azure Solutions Architect Expert 
Microsoft Certified
 Azure Data Engineer Associate 
Microsoft Certified
 Azure Administrator Associate 
Microsoft Certified
 Azure DevOps Engineer Expert 
Microsoft Certified
 Azure Enterprise Data Analyst Associate 
Microsoft Certified
 Azure AI Fundamentals 
SimpliLearn Certified
 Deep Learning with Pytorch, Tensorflow and Keras.
Performer of the Quarter Award for Oct 
15 in Mastek. Agile L1 certified
   Technical Skills
 Azure AI Foundry , Google AI
Antigravity , Generative AI , Cognitive service ,LLM models, Agentic AI.
 Microsoft Fabric Onelake
Warehouse,SQL Server 2012
2019, Azure SQL Server, Azure Synapse DWH, Google Big Query.
 Fabric Pipelines, Dataflow, Azure Data Factory, SQL Server Integration Services 
 Talend, Alteryx
Reporting Tools
 Microsoft SQL Server Reporting Services 
 Microsoft Azure Analysis Services 
 Scripting Technologies
 T-SQL, U-SQL, python,FastAPI, R, Hive Query, Pyspark.
 MS Azure Data Factory, Data Flow, Blob Storage, Data Lake, Synapse analytics, Azure SQL Server, Azure DWH, Logic App, Azure Functions, Azure HDInsight, Azure Key vault, Azure Databricks, Azure purview, Analysis service, Azure DevOps etc. Google cloud including GCP Storage, Pub-Sub, GCP Function, GCP Big Query etc.
 SAP ECC,SAP BW Hana,SNP Glue, Denodo data virtualization and Microsoft Visio as data model tool, Tensorflow, Pytorch,Keras.
 Work Experience
Azure Solution Architect                                                                                                           Sep-2023 to till date
 In-house Nouryon Data Analytics Platform
In-house project
Project Description
 Nouryon Data Analytics Platform is a metadata-driven platform designed to build end-to-end data solutions, from raw data sources to an enriched data warehouse, making data easily accessible for self-service BI users and sales teams to create Power BI reports. The entire platform is built using Azure services such as Azure Data Factory, Azure SQL Database, and Power BI. Currently, more than 12 data sources are integrated into the platform including SAP, ServiceNow, API etc. In parallel, the platform is being migrated to Microsoft Fabric workspace to leverage the benefits of Direct Lake for real-time refresh. Also created Fabric AI agents on top of enriched data to business users to interact with data using natural language 
Designed High level solution design as per standard practice.
Designed Fabric pipelines, spark notebooks to ingest and transform data using standard stored procedures.
Designed Fabric AI agents to build NLP chatbot for business users.
Designed AI knowledge base for unstructured and structured data using azure AI vector search.
Deployment using Azure DevOps pipeline with CI-CD approach. 
 Microsoft Fabric onelake, warehouse ,Azure cloud with Azure function, Azure Data factory, azure data lake,SAP,Power BI.
Azure Data Engineer
GCP Data Engineer                                                                                        May-2022 to Sep-2023
 Enterprise Feedback Loop 
Project Description
 Humana is health insurance solution provider in US. We are designing data platform solutions to accept customer feedback data in the form of call recording, Chats, survey, agents from various sources building customer insight from them. Few applications are designed on GCP cloud and some of them migrated to Microsoft azure. Data processed by EFL is helping client to understand customer feedback and continues improvement in policy.
Understand business requirements from client and analyze the data and key metrics.
Designed High-level and low-level design for the solution.
Designed GCP function and pub-sub message, GCP storage Bucket to process data.
Create GCP Big query tables, Stored procedure, views to process the data.
Create Azure function to process the daily file and stored in azure data lake.
Data modeling, transformation and loading using Azure synapse analytics with dedicated SQL pool.
Designed ADF pipelines and Azure databricks notebooks to process ad hoc monthly-quarterly data.
Deployment using Azure DevOps pipeline with CI-CD approach. 
 Microsoft Azure cloud with Azure function, Azure Data factory, azure data lake, Azure databricks, Azure Synapse Analytics, Azure Devops and Google Cloud technologies with GCP Function, pub-Sub,GCP bucket , GCP Big Query .
Azure Data Engineer                                                                                                                                      Mar-2021 to May-2022
 JCI Data Analytics 
Project Description
 Johnson controls International 
 is American company which produces fire, HVAC, and security equipment for buildings. In the project, we are migrating on prem DWH and reporting solution to azure cloud platform using different azure services like data factory, azure hive, power bi, data lake etc. Building end to end data platform solution which helping to the client for business decisions and Data insights from various sources.
Understand business requirement from client and analyze the data and key metrics.
Data ingestion from multiple sources like sap, SQL server, csv, txt etc.
Transforming data using azure hive with help of ADF and converting existing Talend jobs into ADF pl Involved in ADF pipelines development for multiple sources.
Building DWH in azure hive database storage 
Designed tabular model in azure analysis model 
Power BI reports development 
 Microsoft Azure SQL Server, Azure data factory, azure HDInsight hive, Blob, Azure Analysis service, Data Lake, Azure synapse, Talend, Power BI.
Azure Data Engineer                                                                                                                                 Jan-2020 to Feb-2021
 Evicore Data Analytics 
 Evicore Healthcare, US
Project Description
 Evicore is a company committed to advancing healthcare management through intelligent care and enabling better outcomes for patients, providers, and health plans. Their evidence-based approach that leverages our exceptional capabilities, powerful analytics.
This is cloud-based analytics project for BI data transformation 
 report building.
Cloud development using SSIS, Azure data factory, Blob Storage, Data Bricks, Azure Data Lake Store, Azure DWH, Polybase etc.
Designed Data factory pipelines for multisource data movement.
Data Transformation using Data bricks 
Involved in ADF pipelines development for multiple sources.
Developed Talend jobs for data transformation.
Designed tabular model in azure analysis model 
Power BI reports development 
 Microsoft SSIS, Azure SQL Server, Azure data factory, Azure Data Lake, Azure Analysis service, Azure Synapse, Power BI.
Azure Data Engineer                                                                                                                                 Oct-2018 to Jan-2020
 Coca-Cola Modern Business Data Analytics 
Project Description
 Coca cola business analytics is related to CCEP internal 
 Nielsen data integration and analysis of profit, price 
 cash tool which help CCEP to identify retailer profit, loss, sales 
 price merging 
 risk scenario etc. 
Worked as data engineer on client location 
 in initial phase for 1 year.
Cloud development using Azure data factory, Blob Storage, Data Bricks, Azure Data Lake Store etc.
Data Transformation using Data bricks 
 Azure data factory 
 Datalake U-SQL.
Involved in ADF pipelines development for multiple sources.
Alteryx flow development to extract data from SAP BW, databricks and other source systems.
Involved in Alteryx workflow design 
 publish activity on server.
Involved to build automation framework for data validation in Alteryx.
Designed tabular model in azure analysis model 
 support Power BI reports.
 Microsoft Azure SQL Server, Azure Databricks, SQL DWH, Azure Data Lake, Alteryx, Power BI, Azure Analysis service.
Azure Data Engineer                                                                                                                                 July-2017 to Sep-2018
 GIRFT- NHS Improvement 
Project Description
 Initiation of GIRFT project was to understand the current landscape within SIP and the capabilities required in the form of data and tooling to create a single source for a specialty that could be used across the Program in order to perform proactive analysis and reporting.
Involved to identify GIRFT requirement 
 development strategy
Involved in design, development, testing and code review 
Cloud development 
 data transformation using Azure data factory, Blob Storage
Developed SSIS packages for data transformation. 
Implemented framework using SQL Procedures to load the data into Datamart which have complex calculations.
Preparation of deployment guide, batch file and review.
 Microsoft SQL server, Azure data factory, Azure Blob, SSIS Lift 
 shift, Microsoft APS 
parallel data warehouse
, SSIS, Alteryx, Tableau.
Azure Data Engineer
BI Developer                                                                                                                    Dec-2016 to July-2017
 Model Hospital- NHS Improvement 
Project Description
 The HES Browser Project is to deliver a data analysis tool for the Cooperation and Competition Directorate 
 Economists. This tool is expected to replace the Dr Foster proprietary application that is currently being used by CCD.
Worked on Analytical Platform systems 
 with MSBI stack and Alteryx i.e., Massively Parallel Processing 
 architecture that allows far better performance 
Responsibility of developing the end-to-end database solution which would be consumed by Front end reporting tool.
Worked on BIML script through MIST framework which provides generic and automated solution for the SSIS packages.
Worked on Alteryx for data transformation
Implemented framework using SQL Procedures to load the data into Datamart which have complex calculations.
Preparation of deployment guide, batch file and review.
 Microsoft SQL server, Azure data factory, Azure Blob, SSIS Lift 
 shift, Microsoft APS 
parallel data warehouse
, SSIS, Alteryx, Tableau.
Senior BI Developer                                                                                                                                               Aug-2016 to Dec-2016
 IIS Logs Data Analytics
 Mastek internal
Project Description
 It was internal Mastek project to analyze internet bandwidth in real time. The ELK platform is a complete log analytics solution, built on a combination of three open-source tools
Elasticsearch, Logstash, and Kibana. Elasticsearch is a distributed open-source search engine based on Apache Lucene. Logstash is a data pipeline that helps collect, parse, and analyze a large variety of structured and unstructured data and events generated across various systems. Kibana is an open-source Apache 2.0 licensed data visualization platform that helps in visualizing any kind of structured and unstructured data stored in Elasticsearch indexes. 
Configure the Elasticsearch, Kibana, Logstash.
Create dimension model for IIS system.
Creating SSIS package to load all Staging, Dimension and facts tables.
Creating SSAS cubes and import into Power BI reporting tool.
Creating dashboard on Kibana visualization tool which is near real time  
Creating NodeJS scripts to inserting data from Elasticsearch to SQL Server.
Creating dashboard in Power BI.
 ELK stack, NodeJS, SQL Server 2012, SSAS, Power BI
Senior BI Developer                                                                                                                                               Jun-2014 to Aug-2016
 Capita Data Migration
Project Description
s leading provider of business process outsourcing and integrated professional support service solutions. As part of education services offering, capita has an application called CAPITA-ONE, which is a database used within Local Education Authorities 
 for general analysis and overview of pupil and school data. LEAs store school data in their local data bases, files etc. this data from different sources has to be migrated to CAPITA-ONE system for analysis.
                MDM 
Migration Data Model
 is an intermediate storage area used for data processing during the     transformation of data from LEA Source to CAPITA-ONE. It is transient in nature, with its contents being destructive loaded while running a data migration ETL process. Primary motivation of MDM is to simplify complexities of transformation processes, ensure data integrity and support data quality operations while transferring data from Source to ONE application
Responsibilities
 Completed roadmap for the product, along with multiple stakeholder management and vendor dealings. Project execution supervision and delivery management
Performed the mapping analysis with source and destination.
Map the existing application fields with Capita ONE.
Involved in Database design
Developing Schema, Stored procedures, Functions and SSIS packages using Microsoft SQL Server 2012 and Integration Services to populate data into the database.
Created different reports using power pivot, power view and SSRS.
Resolve technical queries of the resources assigned to the module. 
Timely delivery of ETL packages and reporting during crunch time.
Involved in ETL Testing 
 documentation.
Involved in SSRS reporting.
 Microsoft SQL Server 2012 and SQL BI tools 
B. Tech in Computer Engineering with Distinction from Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Technological University, Lonere.
Diploma in Computer Engineer with Distinction from IOPE, Lonere, Raigad District.
10th with Distinction from VHP Vidyamandir High school, Mahad.
Linked-In Profile 
www.linkedin.com
smitaj-pawar-48a0b077
www.linkedin.com
smitaj-pawar-48a0b077
GitHub account  
themeManager.xml
themeManager.xml.rels
themeManager.xmlPK
themeManager.xml.relsPK
schemas.openxmlformats.org
Professional Summary
Microsoft Office Word
Professional Summary
e463cba9-5f6c-478d-9329-7b2295e4e8ed
e463cba9-5f6c-478d-9329-7b2295e4e8ed
e463cba9-5f6c-478d-9329-7b2295e4e8ed
e463cba9-5f6c-478d-9329-7b2295e4e8ed
e463cba9-5f6c-478d-9329-7b2295e4e8ed
e463cba9-5f6c-478d-9329-7b2295e4e8ed
e463cba9-5f6c-478d-9329-7b2295e4e8ed
33440fc6-b7c7-412c-bb73-0e70b0198d5a
77604cff-8231-44a0-b904-20098cceb947
Sources SelectedStyle
schemas.openxmlformats.org
schemas.openxmlformats.org
datastoreItem ds
A6703DD0-67DC-4FF0-8DE7-E33EDFC9D8D5
schemas.openxmlformats.org
schemas.openxmlformats.org
Microsoft Word 97-2003 Document
Word.Document.8
